<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Like bricks in the sky - Comments: On Status</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2012/10/16/on-status//" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/feeds/comment.on-status.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2012/10/16/on-status//</id><updated>2012-10-18T07:31:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Posted by: Samuel Sidler</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2012/10/16/on-status//#comment-0rst" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-16T23:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Sidler</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2012-10-16:posts/2012/10/16/on-status//</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer custom statuses, instead of a set of predefined ones,&amp;nbsp;but&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you underestimate the importance of each status. While I don&amp;#8217;t use them
all, they all have a fairly set meaning to a lot of people. For example, while
&amp;quot;Away&amp;quot; might be a good status for when you have stepped away from your desk for
a set amount of time (5 or 10 minutes?), other statuses give me a general
timeframe when the person might be&amp;nbsp;back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone idle with a status of &amp;quot;Be Right Back&amp;quot; makes me think they&amp;#8217;ll be back in
5-10 minutes at most. Someone with &amp;quot;Out to lunch&amp;quot; might mean an hour or two, but
I&amp;#8217;m fairly confident I&amp;#8217;ll get a reply. Meanwhile &amp;quot;Busy&amp;quot; means my message might
get&amp;nbsp;ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are all very different statuses to most people, but yet all cover
&amp;quot;Unavailable&amp;quot; for&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also mention that setting yourself as &amp;quot;away&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;invisible&amp;quot; is a lie. Maybe
&amp;quot;away&amp;quot; is a lie, but invisible isn&amp;#8217;t really. Being invisible has its purposes. I
often go invisible when I&amp;#8217;m waiting for one person to get online, but don&amp;#8217;t want
to be bothered by everyone else. Yes, I can ignore everyone, but getting those
&amp;quot;You&amp;#8217;re not idle, I know you&amp;#8217;re there, why are you ignoring me?&amp;quot; messages isn&amp;#8217;t
fun (of course, less likely to get those in a business&amp;nbsp;environment).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I use invisible less and less now because Adium supports setting my
unavailable status and adding an idle time. So to most people I might show as
away and idle for 1 hour as soon as I don&amp;#8217;t want to be bothered. But again, I
might want to talk to one or two people if they sign&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I think this post is incredibly one-sided and kind of short-sighted
as far as how others use chat clients. Maybe that word is idealistic as you&amp;nbsp;said.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Florian Quèze</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2012/10/16/on-status//#comment-1rst" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-17T09:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Florian Quèze</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2012-10-17:posts/2012/10/16/on-status//</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Typically protocols that support multiple &amp;quot;unavailable&amp;quot; status types are those
that originally didn&amp;#8217;t have a status message that the user could type. (on the
other hand, protocols that had customizable messages from the begining never
needed these: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AIM&lt;/span&gt;, Google&amp;nbsp;Talk&amp;#8230;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invisible status is bad for 3 reasons: (idealistic) it&amp;#8217;s a lie, (technical)
it&amp;#8217;s impossible to get right, (long term) it damages the network by making the
presence information (the thing that makes &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; more useful than SMSes) completely&amp;nbsp;unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Patrick Cloke</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2012/10/16/on-status//#comment-2rst" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-17T09:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2012-10-17:posts/2012/10/16/on-status//</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the feedback Samuel. I think part of your comments can be explained
by a terminology mismatch. When I refer to &amp;quot;Status&amp;quot; I am &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOT&lt;/span&gt; referring to the
&amp;quot;Status Message&amp;quot;, I mean simply the Status as set by the protocol (the little
green/red/grey dot in Instantbird, I&amp;#8217;m unsure what Adium uses for&amp;nbsp;this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with you that information such as &amp;quot;Be Right Back&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;At Lunch&amp;quot; is
important, but my point is that this does not need to be a separate Status; it
can be explained easily in the (free text style) Status Message. I believe this
is a more flexible and powerful way to deal with these instead of having a
different Status for each. This could get kind of ridiculous, e.g. why is there
only an &amp;quot;Out to lunch&amp;quot; one, why not an &amp;quot;Eating breakfast&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Eating dinner&amp;quot;
one? Well, let&amp;#8217;s make it more vague and just say &amp;quot;Eating&amp;quot; for all three, but
that sounds kind of silly&amp;#8230;this really can just be part of the &amp;quot;Status
Message&amp;quot;. (It probably does make sense to have some preset/common Status
Messages, but that&amp;#8217;s not what this post is&amp;nbsp;about.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invisible is a lie, it let&amp;#8217;s you pretend you&amp;#8217;re not signed into a network when
you really are. I don&amp;#8217;t think I&amp;#8217;ve ever signed in when waiting for a single
person to get on, but if I was I&amp;#8217;d just put up I&amp;#8217;m unavailable. If people are
still sending messages (&amp;quot;You&amp;#8217;re not idle&amp;#8230;&amp;quot;), then that&amp;#8217;s certainly an
issue&amp;#8230;but I think your client should be able to handle that for you. I use Do
Not Disturb for Instantbird which automatically puts any new conversation while
Unavailable into my conversations on hold (open conversations work as normal).
This idea could be extended to allow IMs only from a certain person (e.g. people
who know I&amp;#8217;m really available during work hours know that they can &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; me, even
though it says not available). I think there&amp;#8217;s a benefit to this as well&amp;#8230;you
don&amp;#8217;t need to wait for them to come on and keep checking, once they&amp;#8217;re online
they can &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; you at their leisure. Setting yourself to invisible is also
detrimental to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; network you use, but that&amp;#8217;s probably a point most people
don&amp;#8217;t care&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it is one-sided, it is based off how I have used instant messaging
over the past 15 years. Your mileage may vary. In terms of being
short-sighted&amp;#8230;I think half of your comments come from a misunderstanding of
terminology. I&amp;#8217;m still not convinced, however, that being able to be &amp;quot;Invisible&amp;quot;
is a good thing, see&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your comment ignores the technical ramifications of allowing &amp;quot;Invisible&amp;quot;. For
example, I talk to the same people on multiple protocols. Some of those
protocols don&amp;#8217;t support the &amp;quot;Invisibility&amp;quot; status, therefore when I set myself
as Invisible, the following&amp;nbsp;occurs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;m online on protocol&amp;nbsp;foo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not online on protocol&amp;nbsp;bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My buddies know that I&amp;#8217;m set to invisible since I&amp;#8217;m not on protocol&amp;nbsp;bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;#8217;t &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; them so I must not want them to know I&amp;#8217;m&amp;nbsp;online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Queue the&amp;nbsp;whining.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally (I didn&amp;#8217;t initially cover this in the post) protocol
implementations of Invisible are also&amp;#8230;rough around the edges, we shall say.
Sending a message to an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AIM&lt;/span&gt; user who is offline usually returns a message saying
they&amp;#8217;ll receive it when they sign on&amp;#8230;but if they&amp;#8217;re invisible&amp;#8230;no message is
returned. Voila you just broke the supposed &amp;quot;privacy&amp;quot; of being &amp;quot;Invisible&amp;quot; (at
the cost of being annoying and sending lots of offline messages when they are
really offline). It&amp;#8217;s just broken and doesn&amp;#8217;t work&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, thanks for your thoughts. It is fascinating to see how different people
use instant messaging (and more proof there&amp;#8217;s no such thing as the mythical
&amp;quot;general&amp;nbsp;user&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Samuel Sidler</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2012/10/16/on-status//#comment-3rst" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-18T06:43:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Samuel Sidler</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2012-10-18:posts/2012/10/16/on-status//</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Patrick, you&amp;#8217;re right. Probably half of my comments are misunderstanding and
apologies for that. I was thinking of &amp;quot;status message&amp;quot; not of status. I didn&amp;#8217;t
realize you were saying these are pre-programmed statuses. But what Florian said
below rings true. Most of those with the pre-programmed statuses are from
protocols that didn&amp;#8217;t have status messages to&amp;nbsp;start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still think that invisible is an important status and I imagine a lot of other
people do too. The scenario I gave is just my personal one. The simple
explanation for invisible is &amp;quot;privacy&amp;quot; and different people have different&amp;nbsp;scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as technical ramifications&amp;#8230; Some &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; clients (like the new &amp;quot;Messages&amp;quot;
app on Mac &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt; X 10.8) allow you to set per-protocol, per-account statuses. So I
can be logged into yahooaccount1 and yahooaccount2, but only invisible on
yahooaccount1. Perhaps any client that implements the invisible status could
show what accounts are set as invisible and what accounts are still set to the
previous status, when you change the client-wide status to &amp;quot;invisible.&amp;quot; But
clients could also show that no invisible status existed for individual clients,
when attempting to change their statuses (list only the available statuses and
not list &amp;quot;invisible&amp;quot; at&amp;nbsp;all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;re right about how some protocols act with regards to being offline vs
invisible. But just because one or two protocols don&amp;#8217;t handle it well doesn&amp;#8217;t
mean it shouldn&amp;#8217;t be implemented as best as possible for all&amp;nbsp;protocols&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Posted by: Patrick Cloke</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2012/10/16/on-status//#comment-4rst" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-18T07:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2012-10-18:posts/2012/10/16/on-status//</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m sure I haven&amp;#8217;t though of all the scenarios (and there are probably valid
reasons for&amp;nbsp;it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your suggestion is what a few &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IM&lt;/span&gt; clients do (I&amp;#8217;m very surprised that Messages
does that since Apple is always touted as pushing the simplest solutions&amp;#8230;). To
me per-account status is a power user feature, it&amp;#8217;s a complication that &amp;quot;most&amp;quot;
users don&amp;#8217;t care about (I have no hard evidence of this, but I only know of a
few instances of people asking for this). I think that this would make a great
extensions for Instantbird and/or Thunderbird; but I do not think it is
desirable in the default &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reasoning for Invisible not being in the default &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; is similar: it requires
some sort of advanced understanding of all the implications of enabling it.
Again it would be great for an extension to expose this option. Note that I do
think we should strive to have our protocols support it as best as possible, as
I suggested in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=802133"&gt;bug 802133&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>