<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Like bricks in the sky</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/feeds/tag/community.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://patrick.cloke.us/</id><updated>2014-07-01T08:03:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Google Summer of Code 2014</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2014/07/01/google-summer-of-code-2014-file/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-01T08:03:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2014-07-01:posts/2014/07/01/google-summer-of-code-2014-file/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m again mentoring for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2014"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; 2014, this year my student is
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sawrubh.tumblr.com/"&gt;Saurabh Anand&lt;/a&gt; (sawrubh), who has been working on a few related&amp;nbsp;things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1024023"&gt;file transfer mechanism for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XMPP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hooking up libpurple&amp;#8217;s file transfer code to&amp;nbsp;Instantbird&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrating &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/filelink-large-attachments"&gt;FileLink&lt;/a&gt; as a fallback to in-protocol file&amp;nbsp;transfers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the way overdue post (as it&amp;#8217;s already past mid-term for&amp;nbsp;GSoC)!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="community"></category><category term="GSoC"></category></entry><entry><title>Community and Volunteers</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2014/04/16/community-and-volunteers/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-04-16T12:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2014-04-16:posts/2014/04/16/community-and-volunteers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It was suggested that I cross-post this from mozilla.dev.planning onto
my blog. This is in reply to a thread entitled &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#%21topic/mozilla.dev.planning/P8oHKTCWSiQ"&gt;Proposal: Move
Thunderbird and SeaMonkey to mozilla-central&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; about (essentially)
merging comm-central back into mozilla-central. There have been many
technical concerns raised in the thread (that I&amp;#8217;m not going to rehash
here). What I&amp;#8217;m more interested in is the lack of community feeling
there. As Nicholas Nethercote said in that&amp;nbsp;thread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;I am surprised [&amp;#8230;] by how heartless the discussion has been.&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should note that I did have some help editing this down from my
original post. Turns out I tend to write inflammatory statements that
don&amp;#8217;t help get me point across. Who knew? Anyway, thanks to all of you
who helped me out&amp;nbsp;there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My full post is below (with a few links added and plaintext formatting
converted to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;formatting):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, April 14, 2014 4:52:53 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UTC&lt;/span&gt;-4, Nicholas Nethercote&amp;nbsp;wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; The technical aspects of this decision have been discussed to death,
&amp;gt; so I won&amp;#8217;t say anything about that. I am surprised, however, by how
&amp;gt; heartless the discussion has&amp;nbsp;been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree, the technical bitshere seem to have solutions suggested by
Joshua and others, but the non-technical parts of this discussion
have left mefeeling disheartened and confused with the Mozilla&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it ironic/amusing/sad/upsetting that a few threads above this
is a thread entitled &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/mozilla.dev.planning/1kbZsYoQcng"&gt;Contributor pathways, engagement points and
bug mentoring&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; while in this thread I see community contributors
being blocked at every&amp;nbsp;turn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I don&amp;#8217;t see people attempting to foster a community by putting
their best foot forward. I see people trying to get their &lt;strong&gt;job&lt;/strong&gt;
done; with an attitude of &amp;quot;if this doesn&amp;#8217;t help me, get it outta my
way!&amp;quot; I don&amp;#8217;t think this is the right way to grow a community. I
don&amp;#8217;t think this is how Mozilla &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HAS&lt;/span&gt; grown it&amp;#8217;s community. I don&amp;#8217;t
think it&amp;#8217;s in line with what Mozilla expects from it&amp;#8217;s community
members (both employees and&amp;nbsp;volunteers!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I dislike the amount of Mozilla &lt;strong&gt;Corporation&lt;/strong&gt; goals
focus in this thread. Can we have a discussion aspart ofa larger
community? Why must it focus on Corporate goals? I&amp;#8217;m not part of the
corporation, I don&amp;#8217;t really care what its goals are or are not. I
care about Mozilla, I care about providing high-quality, free, open
source softwareto improve the experience of the Internet for
everyone. And no, I&amp;#8217;m not talking about Firefox. I&amp;#8217;m talking about
Thunderbird. I understand that Mozilla&amp;#8217;s goals arecurrently Firefox
and Firefox &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt;, but these are not my personal&amp;nbsp;goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Summit I had a few conversations with people about
&amp;quot;on-boarding&amp;quot; new employees and getting them to understand how the
community works and that interacting with the community in a
positive manner is an important part of Mozilla. I don&amp;#8217;t remember
the exact context, but part of it wasthat it is important that new
employees don&amp;#8217;t think of it as &amp;quot;How can I &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the community?&amp;quot;, for
that implies taking advtange of them, but &amp;quot;How can I work with the&amp;nbsp;community?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don&amp;#8217;t see this as an &amp;quot;employees vs. volunteers&amp;quot; argument. I
believe that I&amp;#8217;m expected to live up to these same goals. If I, as a
volunteer, can help an employee achieve his goals; I&amp;#8217;m
[&lt;span class="caps"&gt;STRIKEOUT&lt;/span&gt;:more than willing], no&amp;#8230;I&amp;#8217;m &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EXPECTED&lt;/span&gt; to do that. I think
this is a two-way relationship that must be fostered. It has seemed
to me that over the past couple of years that I&amp;#8217;ve been hanging
around here there&amp;#8217;s been less and less focus on the community and
more and more on the&amp;nbsp;Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand Thunderbird and SeaMonkey may not be important to you,
but it is important tome! (And otherswho contribute
totheThunderbird/SeaMonkey community, including employees who
contribute on their spare time.) When Mozilla stopped directly
supporting development of Thunderbird it was widely announced that
&amp;quot;Thunderbird is dead!&amp;quot;. We, as part of the Mozilla community, have
been fighting to prove this wrong.Could you please respect our
efforts? Merging c-c into m-c will help us focus our efforts on
building a great product instead of spending significant effort on
keeping a dying one on life-support. (And prove to all that
&amp;quot;Thunderbird is dead!&amp;quot; was just a sensational&amp;nbsp;headline.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t have much else to say beyond that (besides thanks for reading
this&amp;nbsp;far!)&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="community"></category><category term="crosspost"></category><category term="Mozilla"></category><category term="Thunderbird"></category></entry><entry><title>GSoc Lessons: Part Deux: The Arms Race</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2013/12/04/gsoc-lessons-part-deux-arms-race/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-04T09:17:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2013-12-04:posts/2013/12/04/gsoc-lessons-part-deux-arms-race/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post title might be a little excessive, but I&amp;#8217;ll blame &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sum_of_All_Fears_%28film%29"&gt;The Sum
of All Fears&lt;/a&gt; that I was watching last night. This is the second part
of a set of posts about ideas I heard at the Google Summer of Code 2013
Mentor Summit (you can read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2013/12/02/gsoc-lessons-part-1-application-period/"&gt;the first part about the application
process&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will explore an interesting anecdote I heard about the
interaction between applicants from another organization that, on
reflection, seemed to resonate somewhat with what I had seen in my
corner of the Mozilla&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization these students were applying to required patches to
be fixed for a student&amp;#8217;s application to be accepted (as discussed in my
previous post). For a particular project there existed multiple highly
motivated and skilled students, but only one slot. Thus, a &amp;quot;patch race&amp;quot;
of sorts occurred where the students competed by continually providing
more patches that were increasingly complex. (Note that this wasn&amp;#8217;t a in
response to a challenge from community members, it was a spontaneous
situation.) Once a single student started to submit extra patches the
other students felt they must also submit more patches to be considered
equal/superior (hence my allusion to an &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arms_race#Nuclear_arms_race"&gt;arms race&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;).
Interestingly, they would also sometimes work on the same bug in a sort
of race to see who could fix it&amp;nbsp;first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a couple things I took away from&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great, the project just had a lot of things&amp;nbsp;fixed!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The students were investing escalating amounts of time &lt;em&gt;during the
application phase&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The students were not working in an open&amp;nbsp;manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#8217;t really expand much more about the first point, it&amp;#8217;s always
good to fix&amp;nbsp;things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although submitting patches might showcase a student&amp;#8217;s skill, it also
relates to how much time the student is willing and able to put into the
application period. This, in particular, matters since different areas
of the world end their school year at different times. A student that
has already finished his semester during the application period may have
a lot of free time to attempt to get a GSoC slot (but will most likely
not have as much time during the actual summer!) This something that
mentors should keep in mind while reviewing&amp;nbsp;applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A downside of increasing amounts of time invested is that the
rejection is that much harder for both the mentor (especially if the
student is now part of the community!), as well as for the student who
has now vested a large amount of time in the&amp;nbsp;project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The realization that actually upset me, however, is that these
students were not working in an open manner! Instead of collaborating,
they were competing! To me, this would set off a very poor tone for the
rest of GSoC. In fact, one of the biggest challenges I&amp;#8217;ve had with GSoC
students is getting them to work in the open (i.e. &amp;quot;show me the code&amp;quot;,
anyone in &lt;a class="reference external" href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/#instantbird"&gt;#instantbird&lt;/a&gt; is probably tired of hearing me say&amp;nbsp;that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; think this is a hypothetical case I made up!
Upon letting it sink in and reflecting on it&amp;#8230;I realized I had actually
seen similar situations during the application periods I&amp;#8217;ve been
involved with. This year, we found a bug in Instantbird&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; code (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTCP&lt;/span&gt;
quoting and dequoting); after referencing some &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2011/03/08/so-called-irc-specifications/"&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, I was
pretty quickly able to figure out the vague areas where people should
look for a fix. A couple of GSoC students in the room started looking
into it and exhibited a greatly reduced form of the behavior I discussed
above. The students were sharing information, but were not comfortable
sharing code. Unfortunately, this led to some very vague questions which
I was unable to answer (or answered incorrectly) and led to me coining
my catchphrase from&amp;nbsp;above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I by no means think this reflects poorly on our students! I think this
is some what natural and expected for most students unfamiliar with open
development. (Extrapolating from my experiences in school&amp;#8230;) Students
generally work individually (or in small groups) on projects and are
directly competing for grades (at least if the course is graded on a
curve). This would foster a sense of competition as opposed to
cooperation! Luckily the students working with us understood (with very
little prompting, I might add!) that we&amp;#8217;d prefer they work together and
help each other. We were able to successfully fix the dequoting bug
(which then caused a bug in the quoting code to be&amp;nbsp;visible&amp;#8230;sigh&amp;#8230;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;short take away&lt;/strong&gt; from all this: remember that students are not
yet a community and they&amp;#8217;re competing with each other until they&amp;#8217;ve been
accepted. (And that they&amp;#8217;re used to competing, e.g. homework and exams,
not collaborating!) I don&amp;#8217;t really know whether I feel the above
situation is good or bad, but it&amp;#8217;s certainly an interesting effect from
the way the GSoC process&amp;nbsp;works.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="community"></category><category term="GSoC"></category><category term="Mozilla"></category></entry><entry><title>GSoC Lessons: Part 1: Application Period</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2013/12/02/gsoc-lessons-part-1-application-period/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-02T20:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2013-12-02:posts/2013/12/02/gsoc-lessons-part-1-application-period/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I briefly talked about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://patrick.cloke.us/posts/2013/10/20/google-summer-of-code-mentor-summit-2013/"&gt;my experiences&lt;/a&gt; at the Google Summer of Code
2013 Mentor Summit. I&amp;#8217;ve been pretty remiss in sharing what was actually
discussed there and for that I must apologize! This will hopefully be
one of a few posts about what I learned and discussed at the&amp;nbsp;Summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part I&amp;#8217;d like to talk about is the application period:
welcoming students, requirements for student applications, etc. Much of
what I say on here is just ideas I&amp;#8217;ve heard other organizations
implement (with my personal opinion on them, please don&amp;#8217;t think this
represents what Mozilla is suggesting students do, or even what I&amp;#8217;m
suggesting Mozilla should ask students to&amp;nbsp;do!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had many separate conversations about what is required for an
application to be accepted. It seems that Mozilla is actually on the
side of one of the easier organizations to apply to. We don&amp;#8217;t (to my
knowledge) require that students have contributed at all to the
community beforehand. It is possible that some smaller communities
inside of Mozilla require more than just an application, but there does
not seem to be any rule across Mozilla. I said I wouldn&amp;#8217;t offer my
opinion above&amp;#8230;but I lied: I think Mozilla should make it clearer to
applicants what is expected of them before the&amp;nbsp;application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seem to be a variety of things different organizations &amp;quot;require&amp;quot;
before accepting a student application, for&amp;nbsp;example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A patch / pull&amp;nbsp;request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; / email involvement /&amp;nbsp;idling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File a bug (I mean this in the &amp;quot;Mozilla&amp;quot; sense: an actual bug, a
feature request,&amp;nbsp;etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix a bug / make a&amp;nbsp;commit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think all of these have pros and cons and making any a hard and fast
rule would probably be a bad idea. Personally for Instantbird, we
greatly encourage students to idle on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; and get to know us; and to fix
a minor bug or two or three. What I&amp;#8217;m always looking for is: use,
passion, and&amp;nbsp;skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking for a &lt;strong&gt;patch / pull request&lt;/strong&gt; (I include these together since
they really just depend on how an organization accepts changes) can be a
bit intimidating for a new user. I think this can be a pretty rough
thing to ask for new contributors that might not want to share their
work publicly with a large group of people (on a mailing list, public
bug tracker, etc.) where they might be wrong. Even after being part of
the community, I find that GSoC students are often very unwilling to
publicly share code unless it&amp;#8217;s &amp;quot;perfect&amp;quot;, but I digress. Anyway, if
you&amp;#8217;re considering &amp;quot;requiring&amp;quot; this, I think it should be pretty clear
that this changeset doesn&amp;#8217;t need to be &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt;, it just needs to show
that the student is able to read code, understand a bug report, provide
a fix and test&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#8217;s perfect reasonable to ask students to &lt;strong&gt;idle on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; and
join mailing lists&lt;/strong&gt;. They should definitely be trying to understand the
community before attempting to join it. It isn&amp;#8217;t just a matter of if the
community thinks the student would be a good fit, but also the student
must ensure they can fit into the&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filing a bug&lt;/strong&gt; is a great way for a student to show a few different
things: they&amp;#8217;ve used your software; they&amp;#8217;ve used your software enough to
find a bug in it (and there most likely is one!); they&amp;#8217;re able to
express themselves in a clear and concise matter. If you&amp;#8217;re lucky
they&amp;#8217;ll find something that actually annoys them and fix it&amp;nbsp;themselves!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;strong&gt;fix a bug&lt;/strong&gt; listed last. You might ask how this differs from
submitting a patch&amp;#8230;and it does! Fixing a bug requires a patch to go
through whatever review process your project uses, but builds upon just
submitting a patch. My thoughts on this are pretty similar to just
submitting a patch, but it depends on how large the bug&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I found interesting is that almost everyone I talked to
didn&amp;#8217;t treat their GSoC students any differently than they would treat a
new contributor to their project. They still had to prove they were
worthy of commit access, etc. Is there anything else you ask of your
students before they apply to GSoC? I&amp;#8217;d love to hear&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other topics I&amp;#8217;ll hopefully find some time to write about
include: community lessons, and handling a failing student. The
community one will be very not-GSoC focused and could apply to just
trying to incorporate new contributors&amp;#8230;but I&amp;#8217;ll include it in this&amp;nbsp;series.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="community"></category><category term="GSoC"></category><category term="Mozilla"></category></entry></feed>