<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Like bricks in the sky</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/feeds/tag/gsoc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://patrick.cloke.us/</id><updated>2014-06-18T23:46:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Mentoring and Time</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/mentoring-and-time.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-18T23:46:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2014-06-18:mentoring-and-time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="google-summer-of-code-2014"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Google Summer of Code 2014&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm again mentoring for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2014"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; 2014, this year my student is
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sawrubh.tumblr.com/"&gt;Saurabh Anand&lt;/a&gt; (sawrubh), who has been working on a full related things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1024023"&gt;file transfer mechanism for XMPP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hooking up libpurple's file transfer code to Instantbird&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrating &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/filelink-large-attachments"&gt;FileLink&lt;/a&gt; as a fallback to in-protocol file transfers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="on-time"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, this is not about being late places, it's about respecting people's time. I
won't go super into this as, Michael Haggerty wrote an awesome &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://softwareswirl.blogspot.fr/2014/03/my-secret-tip-for-gsoc-success.html"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on this.
His thoughts boild down to a single line of advice:
&amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;DON'T WASTE OTHER PEOPLE'S TIME&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this applies to more than just Google Summer of Code mentoring, and not
only open source work, but anything where someone is mentoring and helping you!
This advice isn't meant just for GSoC students, interns or new employees, but
also things I'd like to remind myself to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this sound a little more positive, I'd reword his advice as &lt;strong&gt;Respect
people's time!&lt;/strong&gt;. Someone is willing to help you, so assume some good faith,
but help them help you. Some actions to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask &lt;em&gt;focused&lt;/em&gt; questions! If you do not understand an answer, do not &lt;em&gt;re-ask&lt;/em&gt;
the same question, but ask &lt;em&gt;followup&lt;/em&gt; question. Show you've researched the
original answer and attempted to understand it. Write sample code, play with
it, etc. If you think the answer given doesn't apply to your question,
&lt;em&gt;reword&lt;/em&gt; your question: your mentor probably did not understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be cognizant of &lt;em&gt;timezones&lt;/em&gt;: if you'd like a question asked (in realtime), ask
it when the person is awake! (And this includes realizing if they have just
woken up or are going to bed.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They will not have the &lt;em&gt;context&lt;/em&gt; you do: your &amp;quot;mentor&amp;quot; might be helping many
people at once, try not to get frustrated if you have to explain your context
to them multiple times or have to clarify your question. You are living and
breathing the code you're working in; they are not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't be afraid to &lt;em&gt;post code&lt;/em&gt;. It's much easier to ask a question when
there's an example in front of you. Be specific and don't talk theoretically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't be upset about an &lt;em&gt;r-&lt;/em&gt; (a rejected change)! Part of helping you to grow
is telling you what you're doing wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working &lt;em&gt;remotely&lt;/em&gt; is hard. It requires effort to build a level of trust
between people. Don't just assume it will come in time, but work at it and try
to get to know and understand your mentor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quickly&lt;/em&gt; respond to both feedback and questions. Your mentor is taking the
time out of whatever they're doing to help you. If they ask you a question or
ask something of you, do it now (well...*soon*).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above is a lot to handle, but it can make it a join to work with a
mentor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentoring is also hard and a skill to practice. Although I've talked a lot
about what a mentee needs to do, it is also important that a mentor leaves
h(im|er)self open. A few thoughts on interacting as a mentor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be cognizant of &lt;em&gt;culture&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;language&lt;/em&gt; (as in how well a mentor and mentee
share their common language). In particular, colloquialisms should be avoided
whenever possible. At least until a level of trust is reached.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be tactful when &lt;em&gt;giving feedback&lt;/em&gt;. Thank people for submitting a patch, give
good, &lt;em&gt;actionable&lt;/em&gt; feedback quickly. Concentrate more on overall code design
and algorithms than nits. (Maybe even point out nits, but fix them yourself
for an initial patch.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="community"></category><category term="GSoC"></category></entry><entry><title>GSoc Lessons: Part Deux: The Arms Race</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/gsoc-lessons-part-deux-the-arms-race.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-04T13:17:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2013-12-04:gsoc-lessons-part-deux-the-arms-race.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post title might be a little excessive, but I'll blame &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sum_of_All_Fears_%28film%29"&gt;The Sum
of All Fears&lt;/a&gt; that I was watching last night. This is the second part
of a set of posts about ideas I heard at the Google Summer of Code 2013
Mentor Summit (you can read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://patrick.cloke.us/gsoc-lessons-part-1-application-period.html"&gt;the first part about the application
process&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will explore an interesting anecdote I heard about the
interaction between applicants from another organization that, on
reflection, seemed to resonate somewhat with what I had seen in my
corner of the Mozilla community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization these students were applying to required patches to
be fixed for a student's application to be accepted (as discussed in my
previous post). For a particular project there existed multiple highly
motivated and skilled students, but only one slot. Thus, a &amp;quot;patch race&amp;quot;
of sorts occurred where the students competed by continually providing
more patches that were increasingly complex. (Note that this wasn't a in
response to a challenge from community members, it was a spontaneous
situation.) Once a single student started to submit extra patches the
other students felt they must also submit more patches to be considered
equal/superior (hence my allusion to an &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arms_race#Nuclear_arms_race"&gt;arms race&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;).
Interestingly, they would also sometimes work on the same bug in a sort
of race to see who could fix it first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a couple things I took away from this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great, the project just had a lot of things fixed!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The students were investing escalating amounts of time &lt;em&gt;during the
application phase&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The students were not working in an open manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't really expand much more about the first point, it's always
good to fix things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although submitting patches might showcase a student's skill, it also
relates to how much time the student is willing and able to put into the
application period. This, in particular, matters since different areas
of the world end their school year at different times. A student that
has already finished his semester during the application period may have
a lot of free time to attempt to get a GSoC slot (but will most likely
not have as much time during the actual summer!) This something that
mentors should keep in mind while reviewing applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A downside of increasing amounts of time invested is that the
rejection is that much harder for both the mentor (especially if the
student is now part of the community!), as well as for the student who
has now vested a large amount of time in the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The realization that actually upset me, however, is that these
students were not working in an open manner! Instead of collaborating,
they were competing! To me, this would set off a very poor tone for the
rest of GSoC. In fact, one of the biggest challenges I've had with GSoC
students is getting them to work in the open (i.e. &amp;quot;show me the code&amp;quot;,
anyone in &lt;a class="reference external" href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/#instantbird"&gt;#instantbird&lt;/a&gt; is probably tired of hearing me say that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; think this is a hypothetical case I made up!
Upon letting it sink in and reflecting on it...I realized I had actually
seen similar situations during the application periods I've been
involved with. This year, we found a bug in Instantbird's IRC code (CTCP
quoting and dequoting); after referencing some &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://patrick.cloke.us/the-so-called-irc-specifications.html"&gt;specifications&lt;/a&gt;, I was
pretty quickly able to figure out the vague areas where people should
look for a fix. A couple of GSoC students in the room started looking
into it and exhibited a greatly reduced form of the behavior I discussed
above. The students were sharing information, but were not comfortable
sharing code. Unfortunately, this led to some very vague questions which
I was unable to answer (or answered incorrectly) and led to me coining
my catchphrase from above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I by no means think this reflects poorly on our students! I think this
is some what natural and expected for most students unfamiliar with open
development. (Extrapolating from my experiences in school...) Students
generally work individually (or in small groups) on projects and are
directly competing for grades (at least if the course is graded on a
curve). This would foster a sense of competition as opposed to
cooperation! Luckily the students working with us understood (with very
little prompting, I might add!) that we'd prefer they work together and
help each other. We were able to successfully fix the dequoting bug
(which then caused a bug in the quoting code to be visible...sigh...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;short take away&lt;/strong&gt; from all this: remember that students are not
yet a community and they're competing with each other until they've been
accepted. (And that they're used to competing, e.g. homework and exams,
not collaborating!) I don't really know whether I feel the above
situation is good or bad, but it's certainly an interesting effect from
the way the GSoC process works.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="community"></category><category term="GSoC"></category><category term="Mozilla"></category></entry><entry><title>GSoC Lessons: Part 1: Application Period</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/gsoc-lessons-part-1-application-period.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-02T00:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2013-12-02:gsoc-lessons-part-1-application-period.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I briefly talked about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://patrick.cloke.us/google-summer-of-code-mentor-summit-2013.html"&gt;my experiences&lt;/a&gt; at the Google Summer of Code
2013 Mentor Summit. I've been pretty remiss in sharing what was actually
discussed there and for that I must apologize! This will hopefully be
one of a few posts about what I learned and discussed at the Summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part I'd like to talk about is the application period:
welcoming students, requirements for student applications, etc. Much of
what I say on here is just ideas I've heard other organizations
implement (with my personal opinion on them, please don't think this
represents what Mozilla is suggesting students do, or even what I'm
suggesting Mozilla should ask students to do!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had many separate conversations about what is required for an
application to be accepted. It seems that Mozilla is actually on the
side of one of the easier organizations to apply to. We don't (to my
knowledge) require that students have contributed at all to the
community beforehand. It is possible that some smaller communities
inside of Mozilla require more than just an application, but there does
not seem to be any rule across Mozilla. I said I wouldn't offer my
opinion above...but I lied: I think Mozilla should make it clearer to
applicants what is expected of them before the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seem to be a variety of things different organizations &amp;quot;require&amp;quot;
before accepting a student application, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A patch / pull request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IRC / email involvement / idling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File a bug (I mean this in the &amp;quot;Mozilla&amp;quot; sense: an actual bug, a
feature request, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix a bug / make a commit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think all of these have pros and cons and making any a hard and fast
rule would probably be a bad idea. Personally for Instantbird, we
greatly encourage students to idle on IRC and get to know us; and to fix
a minor bug or two or three. What I'm always looking for is: use,
passion, and skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking for a &lt;strong&gt;patch / pull request&lt;/strong&gt; (I include these together since
they really just depend on how an organization accepts changes) can be a
bit intimidating for a new user. I think this can be a pretty rough
thing to ask for new contributors that might not want to share their
work publicly with a large group of people (on a mailing list, public
bug tracker, etc.) where they might be wrong. Even after being part of
the community, I find that GSoC students are often very unwilling to
publicly share code unless it's &amp;quot;perfect&amp;quot;, but I digress. Anyway, if
you're considering &amp;quot;requiring&amp;quot; this, I think it should be pretty clear
that this changeset doesn't need to be &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt;, it just needs to show
that the student is able to read code, understand a bug report, provide
a fix and test it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's perfect reasonable to ask students to &lt;strong&gt;idle on IRC and
join mailing lists&lt;/strong&gt;. They should definitely be trying to understand the
community before attempting to join it. It isn't just a matter of if the
community thinks the student would be a good fit, but also the student
must ensure they can fit into the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filing a bug&lt;/strong&gt; is a great way for a student to show a few different
things: they've used your software; they've used your software enough to
find a bug in it (and there most likely is one!); they're able to
express themselves in a clear and concise matter. If you're lucky
they'll find something that actually annoys them and fix it themselves!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;strong&gt;fix a bug&lt;/strong&gt; listed last. You might ask how this differs from
submitting a patch...and it does! Fixing a bug requires a patch to go
through whatever review process your project uses, but builds upon just
submitting a patch. My thoughts on this are pretty similar to just
submitting a patch, but it depends on how large the bug is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I found interesting is that almost everyone I talked to
didn't treat their GSoC students any differently than they would treat a
new contributor to their project. They still had to prove they were
worthy of commit access, etc. Is there anything else you ask of your
students before they apply to GSoC? I'd love to hear it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other topics I'll hopefully find some time to write about
include: community lessons, and handling a failing student. The
community one will be very not-GSoC focused and could apply to just
trying to incorporate new contributors...but I'll include it in this
series.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="community"></category><category term="GSoC"></category><category term="Mozilla"></category></entry><entry><title>Google Summer of Code Mentor Summit 2013</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/google-summer-of-code-mentor-summit-2013.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-10-21T02:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2013-10-21:google-summer-of-code-mentor-summit-2013.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not only was I lucky enough to mentor a great student for this year's
Google Summer of Code, but Mozilla asked me to represent them at the
Google Summer of Code Mentor Summit!&amp;nbsp; This was located at Google's
offices in Mountain View, California this past weekend (Friday, Oct.
18th - Sunday, Oct. 20th, 2013).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before actually heading over to the Summit, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mykzilla.org/"&gt;Myk Melez&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/"&gt;Nick
Desaulniers&lt;/a&gt; were kind enough to show me around the Mozilla Mountain
View office!&amp;nbsp; (Thanks to Daniel Holbert for setting that up!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GSoC Mentor Summit is run as an &amp;quot;unconference&amp;quot;, the open sessions
were chosen by conference attendees and run as discussions with no
keynote speakers.&amp;nbsp; This was an interesting experience and how good each
session was varied quite a bit by who was taking part in the discussion,
but overall it was great to hear the experiences of other projects with
their GSoC students, as well as to hear about lots of projects I had
never heard of before!&amp;nbsp; In general the session I attended were about
community building and managing GSoC students, I took lots of notes and
will digest all of this in further detail at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to meet lots of great people from different projects, just
a few of which were: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pidgin.im/"&gt;Pidgin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.debian.org/"&gt;Debian&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://buildbot.net/"&gt;Buildbot&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.opendmx.net/"&gt;Open
Lighting Project&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.torproject.org/"&gt;Tor Project&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.phpbb.com/%E2%80%8E"&gt;phpBB&lt;/a&gt;, etc.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately
being from Mozilla, most people already know what you do...or they think
you do at least!&amp;nbsp; Many people were surprised when I said I work on
Thunderbird and Instantbird.&amp;nbsp; I heard &amp;quot;Thunderbird is dead&amp;quot; at least
twenty times, which was quite disappointing that those in the open
source community don't even understand the current status of
Thunderbird.&amp;nbsp; Many were happy to hear that it is still being maintained
and developed by the community, however.&amp;nbsp; I even had some people thank
me (which I don't really deserve) for helping to continue maintain
Thunderbird!&amp;nbsp; It was great to hear things like this at the Mozilla
Summit, but it was really invigorating to hear people outside of the
Mozilla community excited that their favorite email client was still
being developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People were further surprised to hear that Thunderbird now includes
instant messaging / chat (since Thunderbird 15 or 17) and that there is
a Gecko based instant messaging client: Instantbird.&amp;nbsp; It seemed like
some people were excited by this and hopefully they'll try it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I've gone a little off-topic, but overall the Mentor Summit
was great and I'd like to thank both Mozilla and Google for giving me
this opportunity.&amp;nbsp; If I find any really great gems in my notes I'll
write further blog posts about them.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="Google"></category><category term="GSoC"></category><category term="Mozilla"></category></entry><entry><title>Yahoo Protocol Google Summer of Code Round-up</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/yahoo-protocol-google-summer-of-code-round-up.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-10-06T13:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2013-10-06:yahoo-protocol-google-summer-of-code-round-up.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have to apologize to my student, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phaseshiftsoftware.com/blog/"&gt;Quentin&lt;/a&gt; (aka qheaden on IRC),
for taking so long to write this...but anyway: Google Summer of Code
2013 is over!&amp;nbsp; Quentin has done a great job working at implementing the
Yahoo Protocol for Instantbird (and Thunderbird) in JavaScript
(henceforth called &amp;quot;JS-Yahoo&amp;quot;).&amp;nbsp; It's at the point where it has mostly
reached feature-parity with the libpurple plug-in.&amp;nbsp; Before &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.instantbird.org/show_bug.cgi?id=2135"&gt;turning this
on as default&lt;/a&gt; there are a few minor bugs that still need to be fixed,
but most of them have patches that just need another couple iterations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="where-do-we-go-from-here"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where do we go from here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the last few bugs are fixed we'll enable Yahoo by default in the nightly
builds and, assuming we have no issues, it will be enabled by default in the
upcoming Instantbird 1.5. If there are no major issues in 1.5, we'll remove the
libpurple Yahoo implementation for Instantbird 1.next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-do-i-try-this-now"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How do I try this now?!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can already easily enable JS-Yahoo in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nightly.instantbird.im/"&gt;Instantbird nightly builds&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type /about config in a conversation tab's textbox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type &amp;quot;forcePurple&amp;quot; in the search box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove &amp;quot;prpl-yahoo&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;prpl-yahoojp&amp;quot; from this comma separated list
of values (you can also remove prpl-jabber if you want to always use
the JS-XMPP implementation from GSoC 2011! Note that this doesn't
support &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=14328"&gt;DNS SRV&lt;/a&gt;, however.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restart Instantbird!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should now be using the JS-Yahoo protocol.&amp;nbsp; Hopefully you don't
notice anything different, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.instantbird.org/"&gt;PLEASE file bugs&lt;/a&gt; if you see any
issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-come-i-can-t-use-this-in-thunderbird"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How come I can't use this in Thunderbird?!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Instantbird and comm-central development don't happen in the same
Mercurial repository.&amp;nbsp; I'm working on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=920801"&gt;syncing the chat/ folder of these
repositories&lt;/a&gt; currently and JS-Yahoo should be in Daily soon to be
included in the next Thunderbird release (i.e. Thunderbird 31).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole Instantbird community has been super happy with the progress
Quentin made and we hope that Quentin has learned a lot! Thanks for a
great summer qheaden and hopefully we'll see you around still!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="chat"></category><category term="GSoC"></category><category term="IM"></category><category term="instant messaging"></category><category term="Instantbird"></category><category term="Yahoo"></category></entry><entry><title>Mentoring Google Summer of Code 2013</title><link href="http://patrick.cloke.us/mentoring-google-summer-of-code-2013.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-28T22:05:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Patrick Cloke</name></author><id>tag:patrick.cloke.us,2013-06-28:mentoring-google-summer-of-code-2013.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm officially a mentor this year for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2013"&gt;2013's Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt;.
I'm a bit late on posting this, but oh well! My student this year is
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phaseshiftsoftware.com/"&gt;Quentin Headen&lt;/a&gt; who is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/google/gsoc2013/qheaden/26001"&gt;working on&lt;/a&gt; a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yahoo!_Messenger_Protocol"&gt;Yahoo! Messenger protocol&lt;/a&gt;
for the Instantbird chat/ backend (so it'll also be usable via
Thunderbird). You can see &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phaseshiftsoftware.com/blog/category/gsoc-2013-logs/"&gt;an account of his trials, successes and
trepidations&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phaseshiftsoftware.com/blog/category/gsoc-2013-logs/feed/"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;) or follow his &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/qheaden/instantbird-gsoc-2013"&gt;code repository&lt;/a&gt;. He's made
great progress so far and is able to connect, download all the buddies
and start private conversations! Not too bad for a few weeks of work!
We've been keeping a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://etherpad.mozilla.org/ELTNA6O44F"&gt;TODO list&lt;/a&gt; of things to be supported, please
don't edit it without discussing it with us first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our hope is to get this checked into Instantbird by the end of summer
and run it in parallel (behind an &lt;a class="reference external" href="about:config"&gt;about:config&lt;/a&gt; preference) with the
current libpurple Yahoo implementation. Once we're satisified that it
has feature parity we'll remove the libpurple version and enable this by
default!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instantbird is also supporting two other projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/google/gsoc2013/nhnt11/7001"&gt;&amp;quot;Awesometab&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; is being done by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://awesometab.blogspot.com/"&gt;Nihanth Subramanya&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://awesometab.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?alt=rss"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;)
and being mentored by Benedikt Pfeifer, his code is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/nhnt11/instantbird-addons"&gt;available&lt;/a&gt; and
some has already been &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hg.instantbird.org/instantbird/rev/55009d68c4ec"&gt;checked&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hg.instantbird.org/instantbird/rev/46ee5c836e48"&gt;into&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hg.instantbird.org/instantbird/rev/52401d522970"&gt;Instantbird&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hg.instantbird.org/instantbird/rev/ea36babac4be"&gt;nightlies&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/google/gsoc2013/atuljangra/68001"&gt;FileLinks in IM&lt;/a&gt; is being worked on by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://atuljangra.tumblr.com/"&gt;Atul Jangra&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gsoc-mozilla.tumblr.com/"&gt;maybe&lt;/a&gt;)
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://atuljangra.tumblr.com/rss"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; /
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gsoc-mozilla.tumblr.com/rss"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;) and being mentored by
Florian Quèze, check out the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/atuljangra/instantbird-gsoc-2013"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find any of us in #instantbird on irc.mozilla.org, my nick is
clokep, Quentin's is qheaden, Nihanth's: nhnt11, Atul's: atuljangra,
Benedikt goes by Mic and Florian goes by something starting with &amp;quot;flo&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks also go out to Mozilla for letting us participate in Google
Summer of Code with them again! You can see all of the accepted projects
in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.gerv.net/2013/06/gsoc-2013-project-list/"&gt;Gerv's blogpost&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="chat"></category><category term="GSoC"></category><category term="IM"></category><category term="instant messaging"></category><category term="Instantbird"></category><category term="Yahoo"></category></entry></feed>